<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An ansvvere or admonition to those of the Church of Rome, touching the iubile, proclaimed by the bull, made and set foorth by Pope Clement the eyght, for the yeare of our Lord. 1600. Translated out of French</title>
            <title>Aviso a los de la iglesia romana, sobre la indiccion de jubiléo, por la bulla del papa Clemente octavo. English</title>
            <author>Valera, Cipriano de, 1532?-1625.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1600</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14265</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24578.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116178</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851395</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851395</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16666</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14265)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16666)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 394:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An ansvvere or admonition to those of the Church of Rome, touching the iubile, proclaimed by the bull, made and set foorth by Pope Clement the eyght, for the yeare of our Lord. 1600. Translated out of French</title>
                  <title>Aviso a los de la iglesia romana, sobre la indiccion de jubiléo, por la bulla del papa Clemente octavo. English</title>
                  <author>Valera, Cipriano de, 1532?-1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E. Allde for Iohn VVolfe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1600]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of a French translation of: Valera, Cipriano de.  Aviso a los de la iglesia romana, sobre la indiccion de jubiléo, por la bulla del papa Clemente octavo.</note>
                  <note>Imprint date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: An aduertisement to the church of Rome.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 21304 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church. --  Pope (1592-1605 : Clement VIII). --  Annus Domini placabilis --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Holy Year, 1600 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16666:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16666:1"/>
            <p>AN ANSWERE OR ADMONITION to thoſe of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> touching the Iubile, proclaimed by the Bull, <hi>made and ſet foorth by Pope</hi> Clement <hi>the eyght, for the yeare of our Lord.</hi> 1600.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of French.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>E. Allde</hi> for <hi>Iohn VVolfe.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:16666:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16666:2"/>
            <head>An aduertiſement, or admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>to thoſe of the Church of</hi> Rome, touching the Iubile, proclaimed by the Bull, <hi>made and ſet foorth by Pope</hi> Clement the eyght, for the yeere of our Lord. 1600.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that beare the name of Chriſtians, and vaunt your ſelues to be Catholike members, of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like and Apoſtolike Church, adding ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto the name of Romaine; Now it is time that you awake from the profound ſleepe, wherein long time you haue continued, and open your eies in a manner blinded with the obſcurity of errors, where with you haue continually bin nouriſhed and fed by the traditions of worldly men, vnder the beautifull tytles which by vſurpation they attribute vnto themſelues: for if euer you had matter or occaſion to acknowledge, that the ſonne of perdition (of whome Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh in the 2. to the <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.) is reuealed, and that he ſitteth in the Temple of God, making himſelfe God, and vſurping the power and authority that appertaineth onely vnto God: yea and lifting vp himſelfe aboue that which is called God, in that he taketh vpon him to controwle the ordinaunces and decrees of God; certainly it is now or elſe neuer. And againe if you will looke narrowly into, and examine the contents of the Bull (rightly to bee termed a bubble or
<pb facs="tcp:16666:3"/>bottle of water) touching the Iubile, you ſhal moſt mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly perceiue it. God grant you the grace, that in truth this yeere may be vnto you, the agreeable and peaceable yeere of your ſaluation and remiſſion of your ſinnes in one only Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1. Act. 4.</note> our wiſedome, Iuſtice, Sanctification, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, who is onely giuen vs by the Father, to this effect.</p>
            <p>Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the eyght, following the good and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable cuſtome of his Predeceſſors, as he ſaith, therby the better to ſtrengthen and increaſe the Kingdome of Antichriſt, and more and more to bring in ſubiection, the conſciences of men vnder his tiranny, hath pronounced the Iubile for the yeere of our Lord 1600. adorning and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riching the ſame with moſt beautifull tytles, the better to cauſe his Marchandize to be eſteemed. But as being pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in this ſeate, he is the eldeſt Sonne of Sathan, &amp; that he hath rather ſucceeded <hi>Simon Magus;</hi> then <hi>Simon Peter,</hi> in this pretended authority: therfore he beginneth his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Bull, with a moſt manifeſt and open lye. And to ſpeake truth, he could not otherwiſe maintaine his trumpery, and abhominable errors.</p>
            <p>He ſaith that the Iubile ought to be celebrated (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the cuſtome) within the Citty of <hi>Rome,</hi> becauſe it is found to be ſo by the auncient traditions, &amp;c. But he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſhew that this cuſtome hath bin ordained and appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Ieſus Chriſt, our great Doctor and onely Maſter; Neither yet, that it was euer practiſed, nor put in vſe by the Apoſtles. For as the auncient Doctor S. <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith: Ieſus Chriſt ſaith not I am the cuſtome,<note place="margin">Againſt Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mogenes.</note> but I am the truth. And Saint <hi>Ciprian,</hi> conformable thereunto: cuſtome with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the truth, is the antiquity of error. And if wee muſt onely heare Ieſus Chriſt, we muſt not ſtay, nor lay holde vpon that which any one before vs, ſhall haue eſteemed lawfull to be done: but vpon that which Chriſt, who is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all men, hath firſt done: for wee muſt not follow the cuſtomes of men, but the truth of God.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16666:3"/>
            <p>And althought <hi>Clement</hi> the eyght ſaith, that this inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution hath not proceeded from a vaine ſuperſtition, but of a pure and religious worſhipping: Yet can it not be true, but cleane contrary, for that all whatſoeuer is done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out faith is ſinne; and faith is not grounded vpon the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution and traditions of men, but onely vpon the pure word of God. So y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> then it appeareth, that the ſuperſtition grounded vpon inſatiable auarice, and immoderate am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of ſuch as haue attained vnto this Seate, haue forged this Iubile, after the manner of the ſecular yeere of the Romaines: That is, of a certaine Feaſt and playes, which was celebrated euery hundred yeeres within the Citty of <hi>Rome,</hi> among the Pagans: as in like manner Candlemas day hath been eſtabliſhed by them, in place of the Feaſt which the Pagans vſed to celebrate vpon the ſame day, and with the like ceremonies of Candles and Lights, in the honor of their Goddeſſe <hi>Proſerpin.</hi> Marke then how theſe good Prelates and heades of the Church haue tranſfigured the feaſtes of the Pagans into their Papiſtical Feaſtes, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly changing the names.</p>
            <p>But let vs ſee the antiquity of the inſtitution of this Bul:<note place="margin">Platine <hi>vpon</hi> Boniface <hi>8.</hi> Naucler.</note> we finde by writing, that in <hi>Anno</hi> 1300. Pope <hi>Boniface</hi> the eight cauſed the firſt Iubile to bee publiſhed, to the ſame ende aforeſaid, as hee ſaid according to the inſtitution mentioned in the olde Teſtament:<note place="margin">Gen. 44.</note> and commaunded it to be celebrated, euery hundred yeares. Beholde the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall of the Iubile, edified vpon a good foundation: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde a good ſucceſſor of the Apoſtles, that taught vs a ful deliueraunce and diſcharge from the yoake of the cerimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the Law! and this Pope will incloſe, and holde vs in a much more ſtraiter ſeruitude. The Iewiſh Iubile or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by the expreſſe commaundement of God, was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently obſerued throughout all <hi>Iudea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leuit. 25.</note> not any man for that cauſe beeing bound to goe vnto <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> And this Pope incloſeth it within his Citty of <hi>Rome:</hi> but of that we will ſpeake more heereafter. There are then but
<pb facs="tcp:16666:4"/>three hundred yeares fully accompliſhed, ſince that this inuention hath been eſtabliſhed, and ſo by conſequence, it was not at any time vſed within the precedent 1300. yeares: Beholde the great antiquity, wherewith theſe Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Fathers ſeeme to fight againſt vs, and by the meanes thereof abuſe ſo many poore people.</p>
            <p>But what is this <hi>Boniface</hi> of happy memory, of whome <hi>Clement</hi> the eyght is ſucceſſor? If wee may beleeue cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Hiſtoriographers (as in truth his entrye into the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacie, all the courſe of his life, and his death manifeſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare) he was one that entred like a foxe, raigned like a lyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and dyed like a dogge. Is he not then a Pope of happye memorye? Notwithſtanding, it is no meruayle though <hi>Clement</hi> ſaith ſo: for that the memorie of the moſt parte of the reſt of the Popes is not much better, and diuers of them much more abhominable. The Hiſtorians aforeſaid, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the wicked acte he had played with this Pope <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> his predeceſſor (which was, that after he had perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him (like a craftie foxe) to leaue the Papacie, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this poore Celeſtine went againe vnto his Hermitage: he like a furious lyon, cauſed him to be caſt in priſon, where with griefe he dyed.) Adde further, that this man appeared to be a perſonage ful of great ingratitude and deceit: in this, that being prouoked by ambitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he ſo deceiued that holy man, hauing perſwaded him to leaue this dignitie, hauing taken and put him into the tower of Fumon, conſtrayned him to dye therein before his time; And we muſt not omit by ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, that which <hi>Nauclerus</hi> ſaith, which is, that in <hi>Anno</hi> 1295. the ſeat being vacant, as the <hi>Florentine</hi> hiſtorye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth, Cardinall <hi>Benet</hi> was in great care for the Papacie, not ſtaying till he was called therunto,<note place="margin">Note.</note> like <hi>Aaron:</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon it hapned that one night he went (not with any great traine) to the Pallace of King <hi>Charles,</hi> promiſing him all ayde that the Church could giue, if by his meanes he might be made Pope: whereupon, the King perſwaded by this hope, found the meanes that the Cardinals his friendes, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected
<pb facs="tcp:16666:4"/>him Pope. Behold the holy man, of whome <hi>Clement</hi> the eight is ſucceſſor? ſo the ſuppoſts and vpholders of the Papacie haue a moſt firme argument to maintaine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend their vocation, which is the ſucceſsion of ſuch men.</p>
            <p>To make an end of this matter, I will adde that which <hi>Platina</hi> ſetteth downe of the gouernment and end of this <hi>Boniface</hi> (or rather <hi>Maliface:</hi>) this man ſaith he, dyed when (that is like a dogge) he ſought to procure terror and feare among Emperors, Kings, Princes, nations and people ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then to plant true Religion: that vſed all meanes he could to giue and take away kingdomes: to baniſh and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that to recall men againe, when it pleaſed him, being without all meaſure puffed vp with the great treaſure, by him gotten from all places.</p>
            <p>Let vs now returne vnto our Iubile, which the Pope commaundeth at the end of 100. yeeres, although (ſaith he) ſome others haue reſtrained it vnto a ſhorter number of yeares: as <hi>Clement</hi> the ſixt, that cauſed it to be celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted 50. yeares after, but hee did it the eaſilyer to fill his Coffers. And it is to be noted, that this ſaid Pope, the better to make himſelfe to be knowne to bee Antichriſt, in the Bull by him ſent foorth for the ſame effecte, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded the Angels to draw out of Purgatory the ſoules of all thoſe that dyed in the way to <hi>Rome.</hi> But howe can <hi>Clement</hi> the eyght prooue, that this cuſtome, at the end of euery 100. yeares, to celebrate this holy Iubile is Diuine, and that rather in the Citty of <hi>Rome,</hi> then elſe where? What vertue hath this number of 100. more then any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? What charity is there ſo long a time to deferre, ſo great a benefit as this Iubile bringeth? <hi>Clement</hi> the ſixt had more reaſon in appearance, in abreuiating the time from 50. to 50. yeares, according to that of the Iewes. The number of 7. multiplyed in it ſelfe, incluſiuely compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending 49 ſignifiyng, perfection in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Scriptures: But yet neuertheleſſe the vſe of that Iubile of the Iewes, did wholy ceaſe at the comming of Ieſus Chriſt: and we finde
<pb facs="tcp:16666:5"/>not that any other hath been eſtabliſhed for the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, in a certaine number of yeeres. As wee read that Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme ſucceeded Circumeiſion, &amp; the holy Sacrament, the Paſchal Lambe. And as this holy Father can not prooue that, but onely becauſe it is his pleaſure, and that his will ought be holden for a decree of the Celeſtiall Court: So can he much leſſe prooue, that ſuch a thing ought to bee done in <hi>Rome,</hi> by him called the Fortreſſe and houſe of chriſtian religion. As many words as in that place he ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth down, are ſo many blaſphemies: that the towne moſt giuen ouer vnto all the villanies that euer were; which alſo by S. <hi>Ierom</hi> in his time,<note place="margin">In the pref: vpon <hi>Didimus</hi>
               </note> is called the ſeate of the whore apparelled in purple veſtures: the Citty wherein al things are permitted, where vertue is baniſhed: the towne wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in all ſacred things, yea God himſelfe (if it were poſſible) are to be ſolde. But what ſpeake I of ſacred thinges? All things prophane, defiled, and vncleane, are to be bought by him that offereth moſt money. The Citty wherin the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals, (by the Pope termed his reuerend bretheren,) leade a life more then Sardanapalike, for that they are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to walke with their Concubines throughout the Citty, in the open view and ſight of all the people. <hi>Sodomy</hi> is therein tollerable, approoued and maintained: that ſuch a towne (I ſay) ought to be called the Fortreſſe and houſe of religion? but according to the ſaying of <hi>Petrarke,</hi> the houſe of dolour, the Schoole of error, and the temple of herreſie. But to what end is this Iubile ordained? to reite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and renue (ſaith <hi>Clement</hi> the eyght) the memory of ſo great a benefit: that is, that Ieſus Chriſt the Son of Iuſtice, he that brought ſaluation to all the world, is borne of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> &amp;c. Now you ſhall ſee how this is done: if we ought to referre it to any certaine place of celebration, it were fitter to bee done in <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> where Ieſus Chriſt (according to the fleſh) was borne, then in <hi>Rome:</hi> but wee haue not any commandement, neyther for this place, nor for any other. But, as expreſſe commandement was giuen
<pb facs="tcp:16666:5"/>vnto the Apoſtles to Preach the Goſpell throughout all the world: ſo is it, that throughout all the world, wee muſt cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate the memory of the Sonne of God, without diſtinction of this, or that place. The Lord is with thoſe that are aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in his name, &amp; according to his will. The holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was ordained by him, to the end that wee ſhould cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate it in memory of him; not onely becauſe that hee was borne, but alſo, that he ſuffered death and paſſion, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of our ſinnes, and roſe againe for our iuſtification. And we muſt not attend a 100. 50. or 25. yeares, but we muſt doe it as often as we may &amp; not at <hi>Rome,</hi> from whence the Goſpell, yea and Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe is baniſhed: but in all places, where the Doctrine of the Goſpell is purely Preached, &amp; the holy Sacraments adminiſtred, according to the ordinance of our Soueraigne Paſtor and Maſter, our Lord and Sauiour Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The Pope calleth himſelfe, the ſucceſſor of the Apoſtles: where doe wee finde that the Apoſtles did eſtabliſh any cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſeate, whereunto they haue enioyned vs to reſort, as to the ſtone of faith? But to the contrary, they themſelues went &amp; Preached throughout all the world: they themſelues went to ſeeke the ſheep, and ſtayed not till the ſheep came to finde them. S. <hi>Peter</hi> himſelfe preached vnto the Iewes, and S. <hi>Paul</hi> vnto the Gentils. Now that S. <hi>Peter</hi> erected his ſeate in <hi>Rome,</hi> there is no apparance thereof: the booke of the Actes of the Apoſtles, and the Epiſtles of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> both that which hee wrote vnto the Romaines, and that which he ſent out of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in <hi>Rome,</hi> doe ſufficiently ouerthrow and diſprooue all theſe impoſtures, that would affirme the contrary: for in any of them, there is not any mention made of S. <hi>Peter.</hi> And as touching that which the Munke <hi>Onuphrius</hi> ſaith, that S. <hi>Peter</hi> did firſt erect his ſeate in <hi>Rome,</hi> for the ſpace of nine yeares, and that he was driuen away among other Iewes, by the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Claudius;</hi> whereby it fell out that he was preſent in <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> at the aſſembly of the Apoſtles recited by Saint <hi>Luke Act.</hi> 15. which is but a meere ieſt, and a notable lye,<note place="margin">Act. 15.16.17.</note> deuiſed
<pb facs="tcp:16666:6"/>in his Monkiſh cap: For he can by no meanes ſhew, nor by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny approoued Author verifie it: beſides that, that Saint <hi>Luke</hi> alleageth touching this matter, prooueth him a lyer. Where he ſayth, that S. <hi>Paul</hi> hauing ſtayed for a time in <hi>Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chia,</hi> after his returne from <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> went to viſit the Churches, where he and <hi>Barnabas</hi> had Preached: and hau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing paſt by <hi>Siria</hi> and <hi>Cilicia,</hi> came to <hi>Iconia;</hi> and from thence went for <hi>Phrigia</hi> and <hi>Galatia,</hi> and then to <hi>Macedonia,</hi> where he ſtayed long time, Preaching in many places thereof; at the laſt he came to <hi>Athens,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Corinthus,</hi> where he met with <hi>Aquilla</hi> and <hi>Priſcila,</hi> who not long before, or lately came thither out of <hi>Italy,</hi> becauſe <hi>Claudius</hi> had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded the Iewes to depart out of <hi>Rome.</hi> Now this word (lately) ſheweth that <hi>Onuphrius</hi> deceiueth himſelfe, or elſe would deceiue other men, affirming that S. <hi>Peter</hi> was driuen out of <hi>Rome,</hi> by <hi>Claudius:</hi> For S. <hi>Paul</hi> hauing ſtayed (from the time of the Sinode at <hi>Ieruſalem</hi>) in <hi>Antiohia,</hi> could not haue made ſo long a voyage. Preaching the Goſpell almoſt in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry place, where he paſt, in ſo ſhort a time. And touching the reſt, if it were ſo that S. <hi>Peter</hi> had been at <hi>Rome,</hi> doth it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that hee was the head of the Church? There is but one onely Ieſus Chriſt, who is alſo the true ſtone of the Fayth, whereupon the Church of God is erected, and not Saint <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> Which hath been ſo often prooued by the Authorities and witneſſes of the moſt auncient Doctors, that it would be but meere labour loſt, to reiterate it: onely I wil alleadge one witnes taken out of their own Authors, which by conſequent they cannot reprooue. <hi>Petra dedit Petro: Petrus diadema Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulpho.</hi> The ſtone (that is Chriſt) gaue the Diadem to <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> gaue it to <hi>Redulphus.</hi> Now although this is falſe, as it ſhall heereafter be prooued: ſo is it notwithſtanding that God by a iuſt iudgement, &amp; admirable wiſedom, hath drawne from this lye (that the ſtone gaue <hi>Peter</hi> the Diadem) this true confeſſion, that Chriſt is the ſtone: as alſo the gloſe; <hi>Et Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per hanc Petram,</hi> in the diſtinction 19. C. <hi>ita Dominus,</hi> ſayth: I beleeue that the Lord by this indiction, hath declared no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:16666:6"/>thing, then only the words which S. <hi>Peter</hi> anſwered vnto the Lord, when he ſaid; thou art the Chriſt the Son of the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God. For the Church is erected vpon this article of the faith. Then God hath built his Church vpon himſelfe. Alſo behold what is added in the margent. Where he ſaith, vpon this ſtone &amp;c. That is, the ſame which thou haſt confeſſed: that is to ſay, my ſelfe: for the ſtone was Chriſt: <hi>De conſecrat: diſt.</hi> 2. <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re vera:</hi> Vpon which foundation <hi>Peter</hi> was edified. It is then by a falſe tytle, that the Pope ſaith, that he ſitteth in S. <hi>Peters</hi> chayre: that he is the Father of thoſe that call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues Catholiques, &amp; ſoueraigne Paſtor of the ſheepe. For, without making any long diſcourſe touching the diſloyalties, diſorders, couetouſnes, ambition, intollerable tyrannie, and pride more then diabolical, where with the moſt part of thoſe that haue mounted vp into this abhominable ſeate, haue bin adorned and inriched, or rather ſpotted and defiled, ſeeing the hyſtories of their liues are filled therewith. What duety of a Father, or Paſtor, (I beſeech you) doe they ſhew? Is it in ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Ieſus Chriſt, and al his benefits to ſale? Is it in ſucking the ſubſtance of Kingdomes, by theyr pardons and indulgences? And further, by meanes of the Annates and ſuch like diaboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call inuentions, and all to draw money into their purſes? Haue we any one example of the Apoſtles, which in any thing doth reſemble theſe things?<note place="margin">Sueto in Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berio.</note> The Emperor <hi>Tiberius</hi> although an Infidel and a tyrant, did neuertheleſſe ſay, that it is the duc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a good Paſtor, to ſheare the ſheep, but not to flea them. If wee looke into the trafique, and pollicies of the Citty of <hi>Rome,</hi> we ſhal find it to be but a right fleaing, how much wors I omit. That which this holy father addeth, is no truer then the reſt that went before: for how is it poſſible for ſaith to ſhine, where it is not? Will you ſay, that there is the fayth, where mans traditions and inuentions, are preferred before the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe commandements of God? This onely example ſhall ſuffice; God often times ſayth, and that in moſt plaine and cuident wordes. Thou ſhalt not make any Image, nor the likeneſſe thereof, neyther ſhalt thou worſhippe them:
<pb facs="tcp:16666:7"/>The Pope ſaith, thou ſhalt erect Images, and the likeneſſe of God and of his Saints and ſhalt worſhip them with the ſame worſhip, that belongeth vnto the thinges which they repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. Can there bee any faith there, where the ſimple peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are taught to haue recourſe vnto creatures, to inuoke and call vpon them, and to make vowes and ſeruices to them, that belong to God alone? Likewiſe, can there bee faith where men teach that we muſt doubt the promiſes of God; there where the ſoueraigne Biſhop with his ſupporters, openly, boldly, and ſhameleſly maintaine, that the holy Scriptures, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though diuinely inſpired, and profitable Doctrine, to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, correct, and reprooue, that the man of God may bee perfect, and inſtructed in all good workes: are neuertheleſſe imperfect, and vncertaine, and that wee muſt haue recourſe vnto traditions, which they terme the vnwritten word?</p>
            <p>Where he ſaith that this truth hath neuer bin changed, by any courſe of times. That ſhal be found to be moſt vntrue, by ſuch as will but conferre the Doctrine which the holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles haue left vs in writing, with their inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and traditions; for that the one reſembleth the other, as much as light and darkneſſe, and truth and vntruth. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde a moſt ſufficient witnes of the vnion, that the celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Iubile, where the name of God is outragiouſly blaſphemed, the bloud of the Sonne of God, villanouſly abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and troden vnder foote, and his death and paſſion, expoſed for a mockery and paſtime. This notwithſtanding, this holy Father, the better to couer his ſubtilty and mallice, full of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt, will ground his Iubile, vpon that which is Propheſied of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, in <hi>Eſay</hi> 61. As our Lord himſelfe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundeth it in <hi>Luk.</hi> 4. But beholde, vnaduiſedly not thinking thereof, he diſcouereth his deceipts, and impoſtures, being cleane contrary to that he ſaith hee will doe, following our Sauiour Chriſt. It is ſaid in <hi>Luke</hi> 4. that Ieſus Chriſt accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his manner, being entred into the Sinagogue of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zareth,</hi> vpon a Saboath day, ſtood vp to read, and that the booke of the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> was layd before him, &amp; hauing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened
<pb facs="tcp:16666:7"/>it, he turned to the parcell of Scripture, where it is witten, the Spirit of God is vpon me, becauſe he hath annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me. He hath ſent me to the end, that I might Preach vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the poore, that I might heale thoſe that are contrite of hart: that I ſhould annownce deliuerance vnto captiues, and ſight vnto the blinde, and ſet at liberty thoſe that are bruiſed and broken in peeces, &amp;c. But how did Ieſus Chriſt doe this? did he command the Iewes to whome he Preached, to come and finde him in a certaine place, there to cauſe them to viſit cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Temples, and Churches, and for the ſpace of thus many or ſo many dayes, with other ſuch like follies as they muſt do at <hi>Rome?</hi> Was it not rather in Preaching repentaunce, and amendment of life, and free remiſſion of ſinnes, vnto all that are true repentant, by the faith which they ought to haue in Ieſus Chriſt, without ſending them hyther and thither, with Tapers, golde and ſiluer? And did it not onely in <hi>Nazareth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mar. 1.</note> but throughout all <hi>Iudea,</hi> and in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> it ſelfe, as you may read in the Euangeliſtes, eſpecially in Saint <hi>John.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 25. Act. 1.</note> The like he commandeth his Apoſtles, when he ſaith: goe and Preach the Goſpell throughout all the world. Alſo you ſhall bee wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes vnto me, in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and through all <hi>Iudea</hi> and <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> and to the end of the world. In doing this, did he ordaine the celebration of the true ſpirituall Iubile, to bee in one cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine place, and to be celebrated at the end of euery 100. of 50. yeares? This ſolemne Feaſt ought it not to be celebrated euery day: as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> alſo exhorteth vs, touching the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall celebration of the true Paſchall Lambe, our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt? 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. The Apoſtles &amp; among others, Saint <hi>Peter</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> did they vſe by theyr Buls, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime this yeare of Iubile? Did they not Preach it openly themſelues, going perſonally from towne to towne, and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage to vilage, to announce and declare remiſſion of ſinnes, by the precious bloud of Ieſus Chriſt, to all beleeuers? as alſo conuerſion and amendment of life? They alſo ſent Epiſtles to the Churches, but not to cauſe the faithfull to come to the places where they were reſident, there to kiſſe theyr Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tables,
<pb facs="tcp:16666:8"/>and to receiue a ſigne of the Croſſe, as they call it: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet attribute vnto them ſelues, ſuch a tyrannicall power ouer the Kings, Princes and people of the earth, as the Popes doe. The Sonne of God, neither yet his Apoſtles, did not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point a certaine time, place nor daies, to perſwade the faithful to repentance. Euery day and euery yeare, ought to bee the yeare of Iubile, to all the faithfull.</p>
            <p>It is therefore a plaine mockery to publiſh this goodly Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile. The Pope ſaith that he Preacheth, as being the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador of Ieſus Chriſt, vnto al the world: But who gaue him that charge? a certain number of Cardinals. And from whom haue they this authority?<note place="margin">Act. 1. &amp; 6. &amp; 14.</note> Is it from Chriſt? No, for it was not ſo from the beginning, when S. <hi>Mathias</hi> ſhould be choſen, &amp; others likewiſe that were called to any Eccleſiaſtical charge. But it is the Pope himſelfe that hath aduaunced them to this high dignity, to eſtabliſh &amp; fortifie his realme of <hi>Abbadon.</hi> Had the Apoſtles this proude manner, when they went into any country, to ſend for Kings, Princes, and people, to come to kiſſe theyr Pantable? Did they cauſe themſelues to be borne vpon mens ſhoulders, as this goodly Ambaſſador doth? <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> the Centinier did he goe to S. <hi>Peter?</hi> But according to the inſtruction of the Angel, did not he ſend to fetch him? &amp; did he not ſay vnto him that he had well done that he came? It is true, he would haue worſhipped him, but he was ſharply ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed to the contrary. So much there wanted, that S. <hi>Peter</hi> wold haue made him to kiſſe his pantable. It is therfore neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for the Pope, for the well exerciſing of his office of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador, to go as the Apoſtles did, preaching y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel thorow out all the world: &amp; not to content himſelfe with ſending a peice of paper, to cauſe ſo many people to come to <hi>Rome,</hi> to obtaine pardons. In truth it is a good exhortation that he gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vnto al men, to conuert &amp; turn vnto God. For ſo the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the goſpel teacheth vs. But to ſpeake with the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of ſoueraigne Paſtor; it is the part of Antichriſt, as alſo to aſſigne a certaine place, &amp; certaine daies to do penaunce, and obtaine pardon.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16666:8"/>
            <p>Theſe are thinges that may not bee prolonged, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet poſted ouer til the next day, as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95.<note place="margin">Pſa. 95.</note> To day, when you heare his voice, harden not your hearts. The grace of God is not at this day tyed to a certaine place, but is ſpread thorowout all the world, to all the faithfull, which giue certaine teſtimony of their faith, by a true repentaunce and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of life. As touching that which this holy Father ſaith, that if it were need he would ſhed his bloud, for thoſe that are ſtrayed out of the way: I leaue that to the ſecret iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, ſeeing that there is not any likelihood or appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, that thoſe who ſo long and many yeares, haue bathed themſelues in the bloud of ſo great numbers of peoples &amp; na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, eſpecially ſuch as haue ſought their ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the bloud of Ieſus Chriſt, would ſhed their owne bloud. But the Sonne of God, at the day of his iudgement, ſo much deſired by his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, &amp; ſo fearefull to the wicked, will iudge them. But if Pope <hi>Clement</hi> had neuer ſo little feare of this iudgement, which hee calleth feareful: if he would beleeue that there is a God iudge of all the world, would hee not tremble in his heart? Would not his hayres ſtare and ſtand vpright vpon his head, and all his body become pale and wan, when hee dareth in ſuch ſort power out ſo many blaſphemies, all at one time? Firſt when he ſpeaketh of the Iubile, that was celebrated in <hi>Rome</hi> a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth yeares paſt, vnder Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixt: will you know who that Pope was; read the Hiſtories of ſuch as haue written his life. <hi>Guichardine</hi> ſayth, his Pontificats, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing gotten by villanous meanes, was peraduenture maintay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by more villanous meanes, then euer were heard off. And ſome there were that beleeued (for there is nothing ſo wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and vniuſt, which was not thought to be in him) that <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iazeth</hi> hauing intelligence that the King of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> came into <hi>Italy,</hi> corrupted the Pope with money, by meanes of <hi>George Bucciard,</hi> to cauſe him to procure the death of <hi>Iemy</hi> his brother. All the reſt that write, ſpeake of him as of a monſter in nature.</p>
            <p>And it appeareth by all the diſcourſe of his life, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the reaſon
<pb facs="tcp:16666:9"/>why he cauſed the Iubile to be celebrated, was more to haue money, whereof he was extreame couetous, to inrich his Son <hi>Caeſar Borgia,</hi> then for any deuotion hee had to the holy Church. And to prooue it, at the beginning of the ſame yeare, &amp; as it were at the very inſtant time, when this goodly Iubile ſhould beginne, the aforeſaid <hi>Caeſar</hi> battered the Towne of <hi>Forly,</hi> holding the Lady thereof incloſed therein. Was not this a fayre celebrating the Iubile, and getting of pardons, to oppreſſe poore Widowes, and fatherleſſe children? <hi>Guichar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>din</hi> ſaith alſo,<note place="margin">Guicciar. Lib. 5.</note> in his fift booke. And to the end, ſaith he, that he might not omit any kinde of gaine, he ſent pardons into <hi>Italy,</hi> and all other nations, which are called Iubile, celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in <hi>Rome,</hi> with a great aſſembly of people inhabiting be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the mountaines: and gaue to thoſe that could not come, meanes to obtaine the ſayd pardons, ſo they payde for them: which money ſo gotten, with all the treaſure that hee could by any meanes drawe from the Treaſors and Landes of the Church, he gaue it to his Sonne, that dyed at <hi>Forly.</hi> In the fixt booke he addeth, that he being poyſoned, all the Citty ran in great troupes vnto the Church of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> to ſee his body, and none of them could ſatiſfie theyr eyes to beholde this Dragon dead: who by his immoderate ambition, peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferous diſſimulation, and all ſortes of examples, of horrible crueltyes, monſtrous couetouſneſſe, and vnſpeakeable gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe, hauing ſolde without diſtinction, both ſacred and profaine things, had poyſoned all the world.</p>
            <p>He ſaith that <hi>Rome</hi> is the place which God hath choſen: <hi>Rome</hi> I ſay that hath been in horrour and execration to all the world, ſince the Popes haue vſurped this tiranny ouer the bodies and ſoules of men. <hi>Mounſier de Januille,</hi> that hath written, the life of S. <hi>Loys</hi> among other thinges, ſaith: that the King returning from <hi>Paleſtina,</hi> and paſſing thorough <hi>Italy,</hi> would not goe to ſalute the Pope, fearing to beholde the vices and euill examples of the Court of <hi>Rome. Petrarke</hi> in his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles ſaith thus: heere ſaith he, dwelleth <hi>Namroth,</hi> the fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full builder of the great Tower. Heere is reſident <hi>Simiramis</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:16666:9"/>with her quiuer: monſtrous <hi>Minos</hi> guideth the proceſſe, <hi>Rhadamanthus</hi> &amp; <hi>Cerberus</hi> dwell there. To be ſhort, all mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous execrations haue their neſtes therein: all confuſions, obſcurites and horrors raygne therein moſt puiſantly. The Cannoniſts themſelues ceaſe not to ſpeake of the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are in this court of <hi>Rome;</hi> As among the reſt <hi>Iohn Andre</hi> in his gloſe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe words; <hi>Gens ſancta,</hi> wherupon the Pope will ordaine his church of <hi>Rome; In cap: fundamenta de e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectione, et electi poteſt.</hi> In the ſixt ſaith thus, touching the mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of the Romaines, <hi>John</hi> the Monke, refereth vs heerein to the firſt Chapter of the Epiſtle to the Romaines, and ſaith that Saint <hi>Barnard</hi> hath written of them to Pope <hi>Eugenius.</hi> Which we likewiſe read in the mirrour of Hiſtories. <hi>Lib.</hi> 29. <hi>cap.</hi> 27. The ſaid <hi>Iohn</hi> the Monke ſayd that <hi>Rome</hi> was Found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by rouers, theeues &amp; other ſuch like perſons, that it yet ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoreth of the beginning, &amp; that it was called <hi>Rome,</hi> as gnaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the handes, alleadging a verſe to the ſame purpoſe. <hi>Roma Manus rodit, quos rodere non valet odit.</hi> This Pope addeth, that it is the ſpirituall <hi>Sion,</hi> the holy <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> not according to the letter (but by antephraſe) Spiritually, from whence the law of God, and the light of the Euangelicall truth, from the firſt birth of the Church, hath been diſtributed and ſpread, throughout all the world, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>We muſt not wonder why this holy Father and his Cohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents ſo ſtraightly prohibit to the laytye, the reading of the holy Scriptures, vnleſſe they be permitted by their Prelate. Bycauſe it is the onely meanes to licenſe them, to preferre all what pleaſeth them, and to make men beleeue that blacke is white, and falſhood truth.</p>
            <p>It is certaine that the Church, aſſembled of the faithfull, is the true celeſtiall <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> But what reſemblaunce hath it with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> the which much more ſauoureth of <hi>Agar</hi> the ſeruant, then of <hi>Sara</hi> the free woman?<note place="margin">Gal. 4.</note> For euen as the childe of the ſeruaunt, which was ingendred after the fleſh, perſecuted him that was borne after the Spirit; So is it now. And to prooue it, read S. <hi>Paul Gal.</hi> 5. Continue,
<pb facs="tcp:16666:10"/>(ſayth he) in the liberty by the which Chriſt hath deliuered vs. After that he addeth, all ye are voyde of Chriſt, that are iuſtified by the law, &amp; are deſtitute of the grace: for wee ſtay for the hope of iuſtice, by the ſpirit which is of faith. For in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, neither circumciſion, nor vncircumciſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, do preuaile but faith which worketh by charity: Now to tye mans ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to good works, to induce an infinite number of ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, contrary to the liberty &amp; freedom which Chriſt hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained for vs, to entertaine a great part of thoſe obſerued in the old law, which were al aboliſhed at the comming of Ieſus Chriſt, is it not an impoſition of a moſt inſuportable yoake vpon the ſhoulders of the faithfull? Is it not to reduce a more hard &amp; ſtraight ſeruitude then y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, from the which Ieſus Chriſt hath deliuered vs? And the P. would make vs beleeue that the church of <hi>Rome</hi> (which is this <hi>Agar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 7.</note> yea two-folde more ſlaue then <hi>Agar,</hi>) is the celeſtiall <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> &amp; the ſpirituall <hi>Sion:</hi> but he ſhould rather ſay, that it is the great Citty, which ſpiritual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſignifieth <hi>Sodoma.</hi> But when he ſaith that from <hi>Rome,</hi> the law of God is deriued, &amp; the truth of the Euangelical faith, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning of the church hath bin diſtributed throughout all the world:<note place="margin">Eſay. 2.</note> Is not this a manifeſt contradiction to the holy ghoſt, which teacheth the contrary. The Propheſie of <hi>Eſay,</hi> was it not manifeſtly accompliſhed in the citty of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> when the Apoſtles &amp; other holy men, hauing there receiued the holy ghoſt, &amp; preached therin, went from thence, to goe &amp; preach the Goſpell throughout all the world, as Ieſus Chriſt had commanded them? Doth not S. <hi>Mar.</hi> about the end of his goſpel, ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Ieſus Chriſt after he had ſpoken with his Apoſtles, was taken vp into heauen, &amp; there ſitteth on the right hand of God. And they being gone forth, preached the goſpel in all places. Now this iſſuing or going foorth, ought to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> &amp; not of <hi>Rome. Clement</hi> ſpeaking ſo after his predeceſſors, doth he not wrong to the reſt of the Apoſtles, as if they were Ciphers, or that they were idle perſons, contenting themſelues with the names &amp; titles of Apoſtles, as in truth the Popes &amp; other Prelates, of their tyrannical digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb facs="tcp:16666:10"/>do? for that only excepted, they haue nothing but the bare name. But is it not euident and manifeſt vnto vs, by the Actes of the Apoſtles, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. that when S. <hi>Paul</hi> wrote that Epiſtle, he had preached the goſpell, from <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and all about it, vnto <hi>Jlltrica</hi> &amp; <hi>Eſclauoma:</hi> that is to ſay, in diuerſe places of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia</hi> &amp; <hi>Europe.</hi> Beholde now yee Romaines, how that becauſe you neither wold, nor wil receiue the loue of the truth, therby to be ſaued. God ſendeth you the efficacy of deceipt,<note place="margin">Theſ. 1.</note> that you ſhould beleeue lyes, &amp;c. This holy father addeth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is that happy Citty, wherof the faith being co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended by the mouth of the Apoſtle, is preached throughout the world, &amp;c. Alas, where do men at this day ſpeake of the faith of the Romaines? Is it in <hi>Turkie, Perſia</hi> or <hi>Tartaria?</hi> but is it in the places ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to the Pope? It may be, by thoſe that know neither faith nor religion, but beleeue onely by hereſie: and as they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues alleadge, beleeue in the faith of their Vicar. But all thoſe that know what <hi>Rome</hi> is, &amp; how they gouerne &amp; liue therein, will ſay and affirme, that it is not onely the Schole of Epicuriſme, but alſo of Atheiſme, &amp; deſpiſing of God &amp; his holy word, the receptacle &amp; ſupport of all wickednes. But behold a right papal lodgick: The faith of the Romaine chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in the time of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world: therfore the faith of thoſe that dwel in <hi>Rome</hi> now, is commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded through all the world, as if faith were ſucceſſiue in them, if the true faith did not make it ſelf knowne, by good works. But for that corruption is a thing ſucceſſiue in ſuch as are not regenerate by the holy ghoſt, we might better &amp; trulyer rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon thus: the corruptions, intollerable vices, &amp; Sodomy, that raigned among the Romaine Panims, were known to all the world. So at this day, ſuch vices raigne in <hi>Rome,</hi> not onely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the people, but among the principall of this infernall Hirarchy, are known through al the world. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is not there that we muſt ſearch the faith of theſe firſt chriſtians: for it is wholy buried vnder the earth.</p>
            <p>Nowe if ſuch a conſequent, as this which the Pope al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth, of the time paſt, to the time preſent were receauable,
<pb facs="tcp:16666:11"/>wee might ſaye as much of thoſe that dwell in <hi>Theſſalonia:</hi> for Saint <hi>Paul</hi> giueth the like witneſſe to thoſe that liued in his time, yea a greater then of thoſe in <hi>Rome.</hi> You haue been ſaith he, patrons to all the beleeuers, as well in <hi>Macedonia,</hi> as in <hi>Achaia.</hi> For the word of God hath not onely ſhined from you into <hi>Macedonia</hi> and <hi>Achaia:</hi> but your faith which is in God, is ſpread throughout all the world. Beholde then reaſons well grounded, to maintaine the excellency and prerogatiue of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But beholde one which crowneth the worke, that is, that the moſt bleſſed Princes of the Apoſtles, S. <hi>Peter,</hi> and S. <hi>Paul</hi> haue ſhed all theyr doctrine with their bloudes, to the ende that by meanes of S. <hi>Peters</hi> chayre, being made the capitall Citry in the world, it ſhould be the Mother of all the beleeu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and Miſtreſſe of all other Churches, &amp;c. But if it ſhould be denyed him, how could he prooue it: but onely that it pleaſed the Popes his predecefſors, builders of this tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: for with other proofe he could not furniſh himſelfe. If the preaching of the Goſpel with effuſion of bloud could ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine this dignity, who knoweth not but that <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> ought to bee preferred therein before all others? conſidering the great prerogatiues that it had before, ouer all the Citties in the world? For that beſides them, the Prophets did therein Preach the word of God, and likewiſe were therein ſtoned, and put to death.</p>
            <p>There Ieſus Chriſt did Preach: there hee was ſcourged, beaten, ſpit vpon, and laſtly put to death. Saint <hi>Peter</hi> alſo, and his companions were there beaten and holden in priſon, becauſe they Preached Ieſus Chriſt within the Citty: there S. <hi>Stephen</hi> was ſtoned for the ſame occaſion: and S. <hi>Iames</hi> beheaded, and the other S. <hi>Iames</hi> killed with clubbes: this neuertheleſſe gaue no aduantage to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> much leſſe to <hi>Rome.</hi> The Pope knoweth wel, or elſe he ought to know, how much this primacy hath bin debated betweene Popes, <hi>Pela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius</hi> and <hi>Gregory,</hi> Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople:</hi> that <hi>Gregory</hi> condemned the vnmeaſurable am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition
<pb facs="tcp:16666:11"/>of the ſaid <hi>John:</hi> and that the Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> neuer obtained it, vntill the time of <hi>Boniface</hi> the third, who by the authority of the cruell tyraunt and parricide <hi>Phocas,</hi> obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the tytle of the vniuerſall Biſhop: and yet the Popes did not as then, mount vp into ſo high a degree of ſoueraignetie, as at this day they are.</p>
            <p>For as it is found written in the firſt leſſon, that is Song vpon the firſt day of Nouember, which beginneth <hi>Legimus,</hi> (which within a certaine time, hath been gelded of certaine breuiaries) Pope <hi>Boniface,</hi> that was the fourth Pope after <hi>Gregory,</hi> by petition obtained of the Emperour <hi>Phocas,</hi> one of the Pagans Temples within <hi>Rome,</hi> called the Pantheon: which he dedicated to the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and to the Holy Mattirs, whereby it appeareth, that the Popes as then were not Lords of <hi>Rome,</hi> to diſpoſe of the Temples therein at their pleaſure, as at this day they doe. So this Soueraigntye hath been a moſt vniuſt, and more then tyrannicall vſurpation. All that is added, that there is the ſtone of fayth, the fountaine of ſacerdotall vnity, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>It is to be vnderſtood which S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 2. <hi>Theſſal.</hi> 2. That this Sonne of perdition will come, with all fraud of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice, in thoſe that periſh. For all that, no not the leaſt point, can be found within the Citty of <hi>Rome:</hi> namely, that which he ſayth, that it is the fountaine of ſacerdotall vnity. For beſides that this Pontificats is an vſurped dignity, contrary to the expreſſe ordinaunce of Ieſus Chriſt; tending rather to the ruine of the Church, then to the conuerſation thereof. It is a totall deſtruction of the ſacerdotall dignity of our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But where was this faire ſpring of ſacerdotall vnity, when ſciſmes raigned in this church, more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in any other? eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when there were two ſeates: one at <hi>Rome,</hi> the other at <hi>Auig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non:</hi> and then when there was not onely two Popes, but many times three. Shall we ſay that there is the ſincere verity, where the traditions of men, are in the like, yea &amp; in greater authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty then the word of God? There where thoſe that ſhall haue
<pb facs="tcp:16666:12"/>tranſgreſſed the commaundements of: that which they name the holy Mother Church, ſhall be more grieuouſly puniſhed then ſwearers, and blaſphemers of the ſacred name of God: there where the Pope vſurpeth the authority to diſpence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the word of God.</p>
            <p>He ſaith, that there (that is to ſay at <hi>Rome</hi>) are the keies of the kingdome of Heauen, and the power to binde and vnbinde; but it is an vſurpation, for this authority doth properly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to all thoſe that are called to the charge of preaching &amp; declaring the doctrine of the Goſpell. As alſo that which he addeth that the Pope is the diſpenſator of the treaſors of the Church, which can neuer be diminiſhed. For all the true and faithfull Paſtors of the Church of God, are the true diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſators of the Treaſors of Ieſus Chriſt. And we muſt mark well that which S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. That it is requiſite that ſuch a diſpenſator ſhould be faithfull: but where ſhall this fidelity be found, in Popes that ſell, that which they call the Treaſors of the Church; yea and all thinges both ſacred and prophane for ready money? True diſpenſation, doth it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in making a ſigne with two fingers; to preſent the Panta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to kiſſe; and to giue a peice of ſealed paper or parchment? Is it not in the ſincere Preaching of the word of God, &amp; the ryght adminiſtration of the holy Sacramentes? Where doth the Pope this? It ſhould be a wonder to heare him Preach. So it is neuertheleſſe, that in that ſort the Apoſtles did diſpence the Treaſors of the grace &amp; mercy of God: as wee may read in the booke of theyr Actes, and in theyr Epiſtles. But behold I pray you a right ieſt, &amp; pure mockery, to ſay: that the gates of the moſt auncient Churches of <hi>Rome,</hi> are opened with ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne ceremonies, and that the faithfull are purged from the ſpots of ſin, to the end that the ſoules redeemed by the bloud of Ieſus Chriſt, by the Diuine vertues of the Sacramentes, ſhould be abſolued and deliuered from the yoake of Iron, and the tyranny of the deuill, &amp;c. Is it poſſible, in more manifeſt termes to mocke with God? and to expoſe, and bring in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach the precious bloud of his moſt deare Sonne, then in
<pb facs="tcp:16666:12"/>ſpeaking in this manner? From whence hath the Pope drawn this goodly, yea rather damnable deuotion, but onely from the pit of Hell? The auncient Iubile was eſtabliſhed among the Iewes, by the expreſſe commandement of God. Where will the Pope find that Ieſus Chriſt hath or dained this? which is the inuention of <hi>Boniface</hi> the eight, and that firſt they muſt giue a blow with a ſmall hammer, wher with hauing ſtricken, then with great blowes of leauers and ſtaues, open the gates of his Baſiliskes, to obaine all the benefits whereof hee ſpeaketh? This manner of action, is not to bee found in any place of the holy Scriptures, neither yet in the bookes of the moſt pure and firſt Doctors. But that it hath bin reuealed to his prediceſſors: if it were, it was by the ſpirit of Sathan, that tranſſigureth himſelfe into an Angell of light, that he might induce the ſimple people to commit two euils: the one to ſorſake God, which is the ſpring of waters, that continually without ceaſing run into life eternall:<note place="margin">Ier. 2,</note> the other to dig broken ceſternes, and ſuch as holde no water. But touching the true ſpirituall Iubile, the Apoſtles declared it, euery where, and in all places, as occaſion ſerued, &amp; according to their charge. As S. <hi>Peter</hi> firſt in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that all the houſe of <hi>Iſraell</hi> (ſayth he) may know that this Ieſus whom you haue crucified, was by God made our Lord &amp; Chriſt. Therfore be you repentant, &amp; be you euery man baptiſed in the name of Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">Act. 2.</note> to the remiſſion of ſins. And in the Chap. following, repent you, ſaith he, &amp; conuert, to the end your ſins may be defaced. And in the 10. God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded vs, to preach vnto the people, &amp; to witnes that Ieſus is ordained of God to be iudge both of the quick &amp; the dead: &amp; alſo al the Prophets beare him witnes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all thoſe that beleeue in him, ſhal receiue remiſſion of their ſins. Now faith co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth, not by going a long iourny ouer the mountains vnto <hi>Rome,</hi> or els where, but by hearing the word of God, which is the word of faith; Which S, <hi>Pa.</hi> alſo ſaith, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth; that is, that if we confeſſe the Lord Ieſus with our lips, &amp; beleeue with our harts y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God raiſed him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dead, wee ſhal be ſaued. Harken to that which S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith in the <hi>Act.</hi> 13
<pb facs="tcp:16666:13"/>Brethren I would haue you know, that the remiſſion of ſins by this Ieſus, is announced vnto you &amp; that euery one of you by this man is abſolued of all the things wherof by the law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> you could not be abſolued. Now this was not at <hi>Rome</hi> that he ſpake this, but at <hi>Antiochia</hi> in <hi>Peſidia.</hi> Hee ſent them not to <hi>Rome,</hi> where according to <hi>Onuphrius</hi> allegation, Saint <hi>Peter</hi> as then was reſident, but aſſured them, (if they there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued,) of the remiſſion and intyre abſolution of the paine and culpe of theyr ſinnes.</p>
            <p>For concluſion we wil ad, that which S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith to <hi>Agrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa,</hi> whereof the Pope hath inferred certaine words in his Bull. That Ieſus Chriſt had appeared vnto him,<note place="margin">Act. 26.</note> to eſtabliſh him a miniſter and witnes, as well of the thinges that he had ſeene, as of the thinges that he would ſhewe vnto him, deliuering him from the people of the Iewes and the Gentils, to whome he ſent him: to the end, ſaith Ieſus Chriſt, that thou maiſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen their eyes, and that they might conuert from darkenes to light, and from the power of Sathan, to God; to the end that they receyue remiſſion of ſinnes, and part in the inheritaunce among the ſanctified, by the faith that is in me. Wherupon, ſaith S. <hi>Paul,</hi> I was not diſobedient to the celeſtiall viſion. But firſt I declared, to them that are in <hi>Damas</hi> and in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> &amp; throughout all <hi>Iudea:</hi> after that to the Gentils, that they ſhould repent and conuert vnto God, doing workes worthy of thoſe that repent.</p>
            <p>Doth it not many ſeſtly appeare by all theſe paſſages, that it is not at <hi>Rome,</hi> nor in the Baſeliſques, that we muſt ſeeke theſe great benefits which the Pope promiſeth vs by his Bull; but in all places, where the word of God is Preached, and at all times, ſuch as by true faith doe receiue them, are partakers of thoſe benefits.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, what pretence ſoeuer <hi>Clement</hi> the eyght taketh, as touching the actions of his predeceſſors, whom he termeth Soueraigne Biſhops, and of the conſent of the Cardinals: it cannot be, by Gods authority, which neuer commaunded it, much leſſe by the Apoſtles, who neuer practiſed the like, but
<pb facs="tcp:16666:13"/>taught the contrary, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath publiſhed his Iubile: but rather by the authority of Sathan the father of lyes, who by ſubtiltie and accuſtomed mallice, hath in ſuch fort prophaned this au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to remit and retayne ſinnes, as God hath giuen it to his church, in the perſons of true and faithfull paſtors, in cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it to be attributed vnto ſuch as haue not any vocation in the Church, if it be well conſidered (neyther in matter nor forme) and that make traſſique and Marchandize of the grace &amp; mercy, yea and of the iuſtice of God. And which is more, make certaine Stirrops, to lengthen or ſhorten them, as their accurſed ambition, auarice, fauours, and wicked wils leadeth them.</p>
            <p>If therefore, poore Romaine Catholiques, you will be well aſſured to participate, and haue part of the Treaſors which Ieſus Chriſt hath brought, and dayly preſenteth vnto vs, and by conſequent haue peace in your conſciences; It is not in any ſort neceſſary that you ſhould ſo much trauell your bodies to goe to <hi>Rome;</hi> there to ſtay 15. daies, or a month, to goe viſit the Baſiliskes and Temples, euery day during that time, to haue a ſigne of the hand of a mortall man, which you terme the ſigne of the Croſſe, and a bleſſing: ſuppoſing by this meanes, to haue full &amp; intyre remiſſion of all your ſinnes, as well mortall as veniall. The holy Ghoſt ſhe weth you a way much more aſſured, and a great deale ſhorter,<note place="margin">Rom. 10.</note> when by his veſſel of election (S. <hi>Paul</hi>) hee ſaith, Now the iuſtice which is by faith, (that is the remiſſion of ſinnes, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe expoundeth it in the 4. chap. precedent) ſaith thus: ſay not in thy heart, who ſhall goe vp into heauen? that is to bring Ieſus Chriſt againe from aboue. Or who ſhall goe downe into hell, that is to recall Ieſus Chriſt from the dead. But what ſaith the Scripture, the word of God is neere thee, in thy mouth, and in thy heart. It is the word of faith, which we Preach: for if thou confeſſeſt the Lord Ieſus with thy mouth, and beleeueſt with thy heart, that God raiſed him from the dead, thou ſhalt be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. Then to beleeue we muſt heare this ſacred word of God, as the ſaid S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſheweth afterward. For by the ſame, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion
<pb facs="tcp:16666:14"/>of al our ſins, by the precious bloud of Ieſus Chriſt, is declared vnto vs, in his name &amp; authority, if we beleeue. This word like wiſe teacheth vs in all places to pray vnto our onely God,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.</note> in the name of Ieſus Chriſt; exhorteth vs all the dayes of our life to walke worthily,<note place="margin">Luk. 1.</note> and with a good conſcience, in the vocation whereunto we are called: to liue holily and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly: to labour in good workes,<note place="margin">Ephe. 4.</note> and not to do vnto another, but as we would be done vnto our ſelues. Now for a conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, the holy Father addeth moſt goodly demonſtrations and exhortations. Firſt to the Patriarches, Primates, &amp;c. whom he ſaith, are called to haue part of this ioy. And what? not to feed the troupe of the celeſtiall paſture, which is the Goſpell, and bring men to Ieſus Chriſt the ſoueraigne Paſtor of our ſoules: But to incite them to goe to <hi>Rome,</hi> there to finde his holines, to viſit the Baſiliskes of the Princes of the earth, S. <hi>Peter,</hi> and S. <hi>Paul,</hi> beholde the word which he will haue them teach, and the better to incourage them, hee calleth them, the lights of the world. We muſt not then be abaſhed if the world be hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in ſo great darkenes: ſeeing that ſuch lights are darke &amp; full of obſcurity. Alſo the ſalt of the earth: yea, a ſalt that is not good, but hath loſt the ſauour, &amp; corrupteth al the meate, that is ſalted therewith. For what example of good doe thoſe kinde of people ſhew? Where ſhall you finde more riots and diſſolutions, then in the Courts and houſes of theſe Prelates? Read what S. <hi>Barnard</hi> ſaith, touching thoſe of his time, who neuertheleſſe, were not halfe ſo corrupt, as theſe in our dayes. For that the world is dayly worſe and worſe: how doth this holy Father ſpeake to Pope <hi>Eugenius,</hi> that had bin his Deſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? and how doth he paint out theſe kinde of people in their colours? Is this fellow ſaith he, a ſeruant (for the Pope nam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth himſelfe the ſeruant of ſeruantes) to whome continually out of all places there repaireth, Simoniaſtes, Sacrilegiers, whore-mongers, inceſtious perſons and ſuch like monſters, eyther to obtaine, or retaine Eccleſiaſticall dignityes: Alſo vpon the Canticles Sermon 77. There are very few ſaith he, that ſeeke not their owne, what ſo euer it coſt them. They
<pb facs="tcp:16666:14"/>loue preſents, and cannot likewiſe loue Ieſus Chriſt, for they haue made a league with Mammon. Behold how they walk in proude array, apparelled in diuers veſtures, or of diuers co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, like a Bride that iſſueth out of her chamber, &amp;c. And after in the ſame Sermon. Whom wilt thou finde me among the Prelates, that deſireth not rather to empty the purſes of thoſe that are their ſubiectes, then to extirpe vices? Alſo in the Epiſtle 152. the inſolency of the Clergy (whereof the negligence of the Biſhops is the principall occaſion,) doth in all places trouble the Church.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, that the holy Father admoniſheth them of their duties, according as he doth his owne, yea that which tendeth more to practiſe that which S. <hi>Barnard</hi> ſaith, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the emptying of purſes, then to repreſſe vices: whereof proceedeth the olde prouerbe, neuer horſe nor man got any thing, by going to <hi>Rome.</hi> I would gladly demaund, if that be the preaching of the word of God, if it bee to beget faithful to the Goſpel (which is to bring them to Ieſus Chriſt) to inuite all the world to goe to <hi>Rome,</hi> there to viſit the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> &amp; S. <hi>Paul,</hi> the which Saints, this holy Father, the better to ſet foorth his Marchandize, and to make it of great value: calleth the Princes of the earth, and ſaith that they declare the word of God throughout all the world. Theſe holy perſons neuer once dreamed of ſuch impoſtures, and much leſſe did they require them: Their holy Epiſtles are ſufficient teſtimonies to the contrary: but hee will adorne them with this goodly tytle, to the end that we ſhould vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that he, as their ſucceſſor, is the Prince of the earth. Alſo we read of <hi>Boniface</hi> the eyght, that at the firſt Iubile, hauing the firſt day ſhewed himſelfe in his Pontificall habits, the next day, he appeared before an infinite number of people, armed from the head to the feete, &amp; by one of his Cryers, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be proclaimed: I am <hi>Caeſar.</hi> But who had giuen him this dignity? was it Ieſus Chriſt, when he ſaith, the Kings of the earth, exerciſe, rule and dominion ouer the people, but it ſhal not be ſo among you.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16666:15"/>
            <p>Let vs heare what S. <hi>Barnard</hi> ſaith, in the 2. booke <hi>de conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deratione</hi> to Pope <hi>Eugenius.</hi> Thou haſt no need (ſaith hee) of Septer, but of a Mantle, after the manner of the Prophets. The name of a Biſhop ſignifieth an office, and not Dominion. But if thou challenge theſe things vnto thy ſelfe by any extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary meanes: it is nor by any Apoſtolicall right. It is moſt true that dominion and rule is forbidden vnto the Apoſtles. Goe thou then, and be ſo bolde to vſurpe, or rule the Apoſtles office, or being an Apoſtle, the dominion, &amp;c. This tytle then, doth not in any ſort belong vnto the Apoſtles, much leſſe to theyr ſucceſſors. It is a falſe pretence which this holy Father would lay holde vpon. But if hee would ſpeake the truth, hee ſhould rather deriue theſe titles from ſathan, as from his leige, Signior and Lord, from whom he holdeth authority and rule, according to the wordes vſed by Sathan, to our Lord Ieſus Chriſt: if in falling downe vpon the earth, thou wilt worſhip me, I will giue thee all the King dowes of the earth. For dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Popes haue attained to this dignity, which they haue left vnto their ſucceſſors, by hauing done homage vnto Sathan, the prince of this world. And further, where doe wee finde that the Apoſtles haue obtained this dignity? that for becauſe they preached the law of God through all the world, therefore their Temples muſt be viſited. Did not they teach euery one, according to that which they had learned of their Maſter, that all thoſe that beleeue in Ieſus Chriſt ſhalbe ſaued? Ieſus chriſt himſelfe,<note place="margin">Ioh. 5.</note> did not he teach, that whoſoeuer beleeueth in him, is paſſed from death to life, and that hee ſhall not enter into condemnation? Did he ſend vs to <hi>Rome,</hi> or any other place? Doth he not ſay, if wee cate his fleſhe, and drinke his bloud, (which he had prepoſed before in theſe termes, if we come to him, and if we beleeue in him) he dwelleth in vs, and wee in him. Can there be any charity, to expoſe ſo many perſons to infinite paines, trauailes and daungers: to put them in great charges, to leaue their houſes, and vocations, to goe a long iourney to ſeeke that which they may haue at home at their own dores, if they haue a true faith working by charity?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16666:15"/>
            <p>But I pray you doth not the holy Father and his ſupports ſhew a manifeſt contradiction in their opinions; and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent what ſpirit of error &amp; lying ſpeaketh by their mouths and not the ſpirit of truth? They proclaime with hewe and crye, that in their Maſſe, the Sacramentall wordes being pronounced, the ſubſtance of bread is tranſubſtantiated into the body of Chriſt, and the wine into the bloud. Now Ieſus Chriſt ordaining the holy Supper, would there by aſſure vs, that if wee communicate worthily, and examine our owne conſciences, we communicate his body which was deliuered for vs, and his bloud which was ſhed for the remiſſion of our ſins. To be ſhort, wee are participants of the efficacy &amp; vertue of his death and paſſion.</p>
            <p>If then it be ſo, that Ieſus Chriſt, very God, and very man, is there, (as they pretend) yea in corporall preſence: Is it not a great folly and indiſcretion, to goe ſo far to ſeeke that which they may haue among themſelues? Wherefore ſhould Ieſus Chriſt preſent himſelfe there vnto vs, and ſhould not haue ſo much power in his corporall preſence, as men are made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, that the bones, ſepulchers, Temples and Images of S. <hi>Peter</hi> and S. <hi>Paul</hi> haue? Is it not to make leſſe account (without compariſon) of the Maſter, then of the ſeruaunts? Yea, is it not a deſpiſing of the Lord, who is alwaies liuing, to adore and worſhip the putrified carkaſſes of his ſeruantes? If then it bee true that they are his ſeruants, who will deny it to be a manifeſt blaſphemy? Wherefore all theſe goodly exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, by the Pope made, both to the Prelates, and to Kings, and Princes, are like to Suger and other Spices, wherewith he ſeeketh to ſweeten his venomous drinke, thereby the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier to impoyſon all the world. We muſt not ſtay nor attend the 100. yeare of the Romaine Iubile, to amend our liues, correct our vices, to diſpoſe our ſelues to doe good, and to be intentiue to the word of God, to read the holy Scriptures, to exerciſe charity, to giue honor to whome honor belongeth, and tribute to thoſe that ought to haue tribute; and to pray to God one for an other, and namely for Kings, Princes, and
<pb facs="tcp:16666:16"/>ſuch as are in authority. Such holy exerciſes are neceſſary for all the faithfull, and at all times and ſeaſons. And alſo ſuch as are called to feede the Lords flocke, ought not to attend vntil that time to teach, and inſtruct the people committed to their charge:<note place="margin">Act. 20.</note> but they are alwaies to doe it, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> writeth to the Biſhop of <hi>Epheſ.</hi> yea, in time and out of time, according to the inſtruction by him giuen to his Diſciple <hi>Timothy.</hi> For that following their Maſters example, they muſt trauel in his Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, the 12. houres in the day, without ſtaying till euening comes.</p>
            <p>Wherfore you my maiſters of the church of <hi>Rome,</hi> if you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be participants of ſaluation, harken rather to the voyce of the great Paſtor of al Paſtors, our only Sauiour &amp; redeemet Ieſus chriſt,<note place="margin">Math. 11.</note> who ſo ſweetly inuiteth you vnto his word. Come vnto me all you that are laden, and I will comfort you. Alſo, If any man haue thirſt, let him come vnto mee, and I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh him.<note place="margin">Ioh. 7.</note> Then vnto theſe falſe Prophets, which make you runne from place to place, binding your conſciences, &amp; cauſe you to doubt of your ſaluation. And the better to empty your purſes, ſet before your eyes a fire of purgatory, wherein after you haue bin tormented in this world, by faſtings, abſtinences pilgrimages, and other corporall exerciſes, you muſt (as they make you beleeue) paſſe through, and therein remaine, to be as it were new boyled and refined, before you enter into Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radice. But the Sonne of God maketh one ſelfe ſame promiſe vnto all thoſe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> who by a true faith, ſhall ſeeke their ſaluation in him: as he did vnto the poore theefe, when hee ſaid vnto him, this day ſhalt thou be with me in Paradice: that is to ſay, if we commit our ſoules into his hands, he will receiue them, and place them in eaſe and reſt, attending the moſte happy reſurrection; by meanes whereof, he will leade vs all both in body and ſoule into his Paradice, which is the heritage pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for vs before the foundation of the world.</p>
            <p>This great eternall, and vniuerſall Iubile, whereunto God calleth, and ſummoneth vs euery day, hath bin written by the precious bloud, and ſigned by the death and paſſion of our
<pb facs="tcp:16666:16"/>Lord Ieſus Chriſt, the eternall Sonne of the eternall God, our great King, and onely ſoueraigne Sanctifier. Vnder written by the holy Apoſtle, that Preached and declared it vnto all the world, to be indifferently receiued, and celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in all places, where the name of God is called vpon, and ſealed with two great ſeales of his Maieſty, Baptiſme and the holy Supper.</p>
            <p>Ga. 1. <hi>Whoſoeuer Preacheth any other Goſpel let him be accurſed.</hi> 1. Cor. 16. <hi>If there be any man that loueth not the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, let him be accurſed. Maranatha.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
